Guide to the Fowler and Wells families papers, 1807-1968,
Fowler and Wells families papers, 1807-1968
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Fowler and Wells families papers, 1807-1968, 1836-1901(bulk)
97
Fowler family
.9 cubic ft.
Correspondence, Photographs, Printed Materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, articles, lectures, photos, printed matter, and other papers relating to the practice of phrenology by various members of the Fowler and Wells families, including Orson and Lorenzo N. Fowler, Samuel Roberts Wells, and Charlotte Fowler Wells. Includes material relating to "The Phrenological Journal" and "The Practical Phrenologist," periodicals with which the family was associated. Also includes a small number of Civil War letters. Also, originals and transcribed copies of the wills of Charlotte Fowler Howe and Charlotte Fowler Wells, and other letters.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, articles, lectures, photos, printed matter, and other papers relating to the practice of phrenology by various members of the Fowler and Wells families, including Orson and Lorenzo N. Fowler, Samuel Roberts Wells, and Charlotte Fowler Wells. Includes material relating to "The Phrenological Journal" and "The Practical Phrenologist," periodicals with which the family was associated. Also includes a small number of Civil War letters. Also, originals and transcribed copies of the wills of Charlotte Fowler Howe and Charlotte Fowler Wells, and other letters.
Correspondents include Susan B. Anthony, F.A.P. Barnard, Albert Barnes, Antoinette Brown, James Freeman Clarke, William H. Channing, John W. Edmonds, Frederick W. Evans, O.B. Frothingham, Frances Dana Gage, Sylvester Graham, Sarah Grimké, Bronson Howard, Horace Mann, Eliphalet Nott, George Ripley, Benjamin Silliman, George Francis Train, Moses Coit Tyler, Benjamin F. Wade, and Elizur Wright. HOWE-FOWLER FAMILY LETTERS, bound volume of transcribed letters by Harlan L. Howe.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Fowler family.; Fowler, O. S. (Orson Squire), 1809-1887.; Fowler, L. N. (Lorenzo Niles), 1811-1896.; Wells, Samuel R. (Samuel Roberts), 1820-1875.; Wells, Charlotte Fowler, 1814-1901.; Wells family.; Anthony, Susan B. (Susan Brownell), 1820-1906.; Barnard, Frederick A. P. (Frederick Augustus Porter), 1809-1889.; Barnes, Albert, 1798-1870.; Blackwell, Antoinette Louisa Brown, 1825-1921.; Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888.; Channing, W. H. (William Henry), 1810-1884.; Edmonds, John W. (John Worth), 1799-1874.; Evans, F. W. (Frederick William), 1808-1893.; Frothingham, Octavius Brooks, 1822-1895.; Gage, Frances Dana, 1808-1884.; Graham, Sylvester, 1794-1851.; Grimké, Sarah Moore, 1792-1873.; Howard, Bronson, 1842-1908.; Mann, Horace, 1796-1859.; Nott, Eliphalet, 1773-1866.; Ripley, George, 1802-1880.; Silliman, Benjamin, 1816-1885.; Train, George Francis, 1829-1904.; Tyler, Moses Coit, 1835-1900.; Wade, Benjamin F. (Benjamin Franklin), 1800-1878.; Anthony, Susan B. (Susan Brownell), 1820-1906; Barnard, Frederick A. P. (Frederick Augustus Porter), 1809-1889; Barnes, Albert, 1798-1870; Blackwell, Antoinette Louisa Brown, 1825-1921; Clarke, James Freeman, 1810-1888; Edmonds, John W. (John Worth), 1799-1874; Evans, F. W. (Frederick William), 1808-1893; Fowler, L. N. (Lorenzo Niles), 1811-1896; Fowler, O. S. (Orson Squire), 1809-1887; Frothingham, Octavius Brooks, 1822-1895; Gage, Frances Dana, 1808-1884; Graham, Sylvester, 1794-1851; Grimké, Sarah Moore, 1792-1873; Howard, Bronson, 1842-1908; Mann, Horace, 1796-1859; Nott, Eliphalet, 1773-1866; Silliman, Benjamin, 1816-1885; Train, George Francis, 1829-1904; Tyler, Moses Coit, 1835-1900; Wade, Benjamin F. (Benjamin Franklin), 1800-1878; Wells, Charlotte Fowler, 1814-1901; Wells family; Wells, Samuel R. (Samuel Roberts), 1820-1875; Howe, Harlan L.; American Civil War (1861-1865)
Titles:
The phrenological journal.; The practical phrenologist.
Subjects:
Phrenology.
Places:
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
A PDF with additional details is available upon request.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence and Family Papers
Series II. Photographs
CONTAINER LIST
- Correspondence and Family Papers
  Arranged in chronological order and then by physical location.
  - Synopsis of Phrenology and the Phrenological Developments Together with the Character and Talents of Paul S. Howe, Esq., as given by Charlotte Fowler, 1846-DateTo (Box 2)
    Howe, Paul S.
    Fowler, Charlotte
  - Synopsis of Phrenology and the Phrenological Developments Together with the Character and Talents of Philip C. Howard, as given by Lorenzo Fowler, 1846-06-08 (Box 2)
    Howard, Philip C.
    Fowler, Lorenzo
  - Letters, 1848-1859 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Papers, 1849-1892 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript report by Mrs. Wells of spiritualist meetings held in New York City during 1850 with comments on the participation of Horace Greeley and other notables, 1850 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Mrs. Wells
    New York City
  - The Illustrated Self-Instructor in Phrenology and Physiology with One Hundred Engravings and a Chart of the Character of Paul Howe, as given by Nelson Sizer, 1851-10-24 (Box 2)
    Howe, Paul
    Sizer, Nelson
  - Letters, 1860-1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1868-1869 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1870-1872 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1873-1879 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters, 1881-1887, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Practice of the Water Cure, 1891-08; Wilson, James; Manby Gully, James (Box 2)
    New York
  - Ulrich is Domestic, 1899-01; Human Nature IX #1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Poe: "The Mental Temperament" for Phrenologists, 1968-05; Stern, Madeline B.; American Literature Vol. XL, No. 2 (Box 2)
  - Index and handwritten genealogy, 1993; Howe, Harlan L. (Box 4)
  - Fowler and Wells family letters (c. 113 - primarily from Charlotte Fowler Wells to Paul Howe) and envelopes, Date Unknown (Box 4)
    Fowler Wells, Charlotte
  - Copies of obituaries of Charlotte Fowler Wells and Lydia Folger Fowler, Date Unknown (Box 4)
    Folger Fowler, Lydia
  - Undated and Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Anthony, Susan B.
  - Phrenological Dictionary, Undated; Fowler, Lorenzo; Fowler, Jessie A. (Box 2)
    London
  - Professor Lorenzo Fowler - A biographical Sketch also includes Facts About Mesmerism, Undated; Fowler, Lorenzo (Box 2)
  - Papers, Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Papers, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Typescript transcripts, Undated (Box 4)
  - Letter from Horace Greeley to Dr. Almira L. Fowler, Undated; Greeley, Horace (Box 4)
    Greeley, Horace
    Fowler, Almira L.
  - Typescript transcript copies of phrenological descriptions, Undated (Box 4)
  - Copy of will of Charlotte Fowler Howe, Undated; Fowler Howe, Charlotee (Box 4)
  - Howe-Fowler family letters, Undated (Box 4)
    Howe
    Fowler
  - Bound volume of transcribed letters, Undated (Box 4)
  - Phrenological studies, Undated (Box 5)
  - Clippings, Undated (Box 5)
- Photographs
  Arranged by physical location.
  - 11 Photographs, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 6 Engravings and 2 Photographs of Engravings, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Group photograph including Mrs. Wells, as indicated on reverse, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 5 photographs (plus 1 duplicate), Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 5 photographs (3 of S.R. Wells), Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Group photograph including Mrs. Wells, as indicated on reverse, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Fowler, Lorenzo and Amelia
  - Photographs (3), Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Fowler, Amelia
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Fowler, Jessie
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Fowler, Mrs. Lorenzo
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Wells, Charlotte F.
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Wells, S.R.
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Fowler, Edward
  - Photograph, group, Undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    England
  - Photograph, 5 persons (Office group), Undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 5)